<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-03T09:30:47-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Brandon (Shuba) Marrow</title><subtitle>Brandon (Shuba) Marrow's writing, projects, and music.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Images from Western Siberia 2: Tets-5</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/17/Images-from-Western-Siberia-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Images from Western Siberia 2: Tets-5" /><published>2019-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/17/Images-from-Western-Siberia-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/17/Images-from-Western-Siberia-2">&lt;h2 id=&quot;tets-5&quot;&gt;Tets-5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the kind of blindingly bright day typical of Novosibirsk’s winters. As I walked out of the university, bleary-eyed and zipped into a loon-down jacket, I noticed a particularly fine cloud developing on the horizon. I did not pause as I should have as that word &lt;strong&gt;developing&lt;/strong&gt; crossed my mind. The wind was not blowing, but the cloud accumulated nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounding the corner towards the &lt;a href=&quot;./2019-02-26-GAZeli-on-a-Not-So-Open_Plain.md&quot;&gt;marshrutka&lt;/a&gt; stop, eyes still glued to the cloud, the long perspective of Vybornaya street came into view. The leftmost side of this visage, that on the side of the street leading to the city center, was decorated by the pine trunks of Iniushenskii bor (“In-you-shin-ski” forest), one of the only forests within the city limits. The rightmost was crowded by ten-floor apartment buildings, a small shopping center (Торговый центр), and, finally, the cloud that caught my eye. Tracing the outline of the cloud from its heights to the horizon, I made a shocking discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/tets-5.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The cloud generator. Photo credit: Erin McConnell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was yet to move to Vybornaya street and, apparently, still very unfamiliar with the major features of the area, which represented the outer limit of the October district. These Simpsons-style smokestacks (Hyperboloid cooling towers) belch steam produced by the coal-fired plant located at the end of Vybornaya street known as Tets-5 (Thermal Power Plant Number 5). When I later moved into a tenth-floor apartment on Vybornaya street, Tets-5 came to dominate the view from the left side of my window, putting the Iniushenskii forest on the other side in serious industrial relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While other Siberian cities rely more heavily on &lt;a href=&quot;./2019-11-13-Images-from-Western-Siberia.md&quot;&gt;hydroelectric power&lt;/a&gt;, Novosibirsk depends on coal-fired plants like Tets-5 to keep the waves of electric heat radiating from the famous Soviet &lt;strong&gt;батареи&lt;/strong&gt; (radiators). They dry heat emanating from the radiators for nine months of the year has been ironically dubbed the “Siberian summer” by locals. To be clear, the company running these plants–The Siberian Generating Company (&lt;a href=&quot;https://sibgenco.ru/about/company/generation&quot;&gt;SibGenCo&lt;/a&gt;)–wants locals to be proud of these massive plants keeping the heat on. An advertisement appeared in my apartment building’s elevator one day inviting residents of Vybornaya street to come take a tour of the facility, the largest modular thermal-energy center in Siberia, providing energy to 35% (800,000) of Novosibirsk’s residents. These impressive numbers come at a cost, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after I returned to America in July, news articles about Tets-5 appeared in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-48935401&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cosmopolitan.com/entertainment/celebs/a28361892/instagrammers-turquoise-lake-toxic-dump/&quot;&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/salvadorhernandez/instagram-selfies-toxic-lake-russia&quot;&gt;BuzzFeed&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of touting the impressive energy output of the plant, these articles focused on what was done with the waste product. Waste from the burning coal was trucked to a lake directly behind the plant and dumped, a process which turned the lake a bright turquoise color. The tropical color of the lake attracted locals seeking tropical Instagram pictures without the tropical vacation and soon the area received an appropriate name, the “Novosibirsk Maldives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I never visited Novosibirsk’s Maldives, I can attest to the magnetic force of an exotic Instagram backdrop, especially for Siberians, many of whom cannot afford a far-flung international vacation. Many of the articles written about Siberians flocking to the lake are written with the assumption that those visiting it were not aware that it was a toxic dump. While this may have been true for some, the lake’s proximity to the enormous coal plant would have made that fact obvious for locals. It is doubtful that any of those visiting weren’t aware of the fact that it was the waste from the plant that was turning the lake blue. And so this story tells a different story about Siberians, not a tale of reckless abandon, but of dedication and persistence in the pursuit of Instagram glory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Brandon Marrow</name></author><summary type="html">Tets-5 It was the kind of blindingly bright day typical of Novosibirsk’s winters. As I walked out of the university, bleary-eyed and zipped into a loon-down jacket, I noticed a particularly fine cloud developing on the horizon. I did not pause as I should have as that word developing crossed my mind. The wind was not blowing, but the cloud accumulated nonetheless.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Images from Western Siberia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/Images-from-Western-Siberia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Images from Western Siberia" /><published>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/Images-from-Western-Siberia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/Images-from-Western-Siberia">&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-the-ob-sea&quot;&gt;1. The Ob’ Sea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post marks the beginning of what I hope to be a series of posts about my experiences in Siberia. Inspired by the photos I took there, this blog will include my reflections and, in some cases, the first-hand observations I recorded while living in Novosibirsk.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/obskoe-more.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Обское море (The Ob’ Sea)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption is misleading. The water lapping the shore certainly suggests an oceanic landscape, but what you are looking at is one of the many artificial lakes that litter the Siberian landscape. The lakes were created by the construction of a dam powering a hydro-electric station, what in Russian is known as a &lt;em&gt;ГЭС&lt;/em&gt; (pronounced like “guess”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hydroelectric station was built from 1950-1959 along with a number of hydroelectric stations in Siberia. The station was intended to help power the large influx of industry in Novosibirsk engendered by the evacuation of factories from Western Russia during the war. However, unlike the raging rivers of Eastern Siberia (e.g., the Angara in Irkutsk), the power created from damming the Ob’ river did not suffice. To this day, the vast majority of Novosibirsk’s energy comes from its coal fired plants. Nonetheless, a point of pride for Novosibirsk and Siberian hydroelectric stationis in general, is that they were constructed with far less political prisoner labor than those of Western Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/five-year-ges.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A post showing similar projects undertaken in the post-war period in Western Russia near the Caspian sea. The poster reads: The post-war five-year plan has been exceeded. The development of electro-energy in the last year of the five-year plan was supposed to have grown 70% from the pre-war period. Instead it amazingly grew by 80%.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These artificial lakes achieved a mythical status for a variety of reasons. For one, the whole process of electrification was romanticized in Soviet Propaganda as a process of harnessing nature and subjecting it to human control. In Novosibirsk, this is particularly ironic because the artificial lake actually increased wind speeds and changed weather patterns in the city given its enormous surface area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another myth surrounding these areas has to do with the areas they flooded. The artificial lakes almost always flooded the areas of former villages, the residents of which had to be resettled. In the Novosibirsk region, the old city of Berdsk had to be completely relocated and constructed anew. This process had particular resonance with a mythical Russian city known as Kitezh. According to the myth, the citizens of Kitezh prayed for salvation from an invading Tatar army and as a result were flooded with their city under the depths of Lake Svetloyar. The legend holds that the sound of the city’s church bells and the noise from its services can still be heard from the surface of the lake. Though I heard no bells, I can see how the wind gusting along the surface could inspire such impressions in the minds of those with the legend in their heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/berdsk-water-tower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A water tower near school number 5 in the new city of Berdsk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Brandon Marrow</name></author><summary type="html">1. The Ob’ Sea This post marks the beginning of what I hope to be a series of posts about my experiences in Siberia. Inspired by the photos I took there, this blog will include my reflections and, in some cases, the first-hand observations I recorded while living in Novosibirsk. Обское море (The Ob’ Sea)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GAZeli on a Not So Open Plain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/02/26/GAZeli-on-a-Not-So-Open_Plain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GAZeli on a Not So Open Plain" /><published>2019-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/02/26/GAZeli-on-a-Not-So-Open_Plain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2019/02/26/GAZeli-on-a-Not-So-Open_Plain">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-marshrutka-stampede-in-novosibirsk&quot;&gt;The Marshrutka Stampede in Novosibirsk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a story about what my daily commute has taught me about Novosibirsk and how the life of the city is reflected in a certain mode of transport - the so called marshrutnoye taksi (‘fixed-route taxi’), marshrutka for short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/daily-commute.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Novosibirsk, Novosibirskaia Oblast’.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://2gis.ru/novosibirsk&quot;&gt;Map from 2gis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map above outlines the three legs of my daily commute. The first leg is pictured in green and represents travel from the metro station “Marshall Pokryshkin” to the metro station “Sibirskaia” (Siberian). After crossing through an underground tunnel, I embark on the second (red) leg of my journey from the metro station “Krasnyi Prospekt” to the “Oktiabrskaia” station. From Oktiabrskaia, I emerge from the metro to wait at the bus stop, at which point the real fun begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the bus stop, me and most of the student body of the Novosibirsk State Pedagogical University (NGPU) nervously scan the October thoroughfare for incoming transport that will whisk us the rest of the way to the university (point Б on the map). There are only three options we can hope for - the 18 bus, the 75 microbus (a “Pazik,” more on this later), and the 45 marshrutka. Of these three, the 18 and the 75 are fickle ghosts the punctual student commuter cannot depend upon; the 45 marshrutka (make: GAZel’ Next) is by far the best bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/gazel-next.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The GAZel’ Next, route number 44. The name is a pun mixing the Russian word for gazelle with the name of the company that makes the vehicle - GAZ (‘gas’). &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdelanounas.ru/blogs/51457/&quot;&gt;Picture Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, for all the 45’s frequency, it is plagued by a disease endemic to most of Novosibirsk’s ungulates on wheels - overcrowding. As the 45 pulls up to Oktiabrskaia, its front door swings open to reveal a crush of passengers. Out of those waiting on the bus stop, the most daring (read: aggressive) throw themselves with abandon into the mass, the most timid cling to their hopes that the next won’t be so full. In order to get to the university on time, I try to politely pack myself into the marshrutka, imagining my students and colleagues’ frustration were I to arrive late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the ride is only 20 minutes, it is a thoroughly transformative journey. Often I find myself functioning as a door, pushed so far back onto the steps leading to the main cabin that the door and I move with the same pneumatic inswing. At other times, I become a human blind spot, crammed into the front corner of the ungulate such that I obscure the passenger-side mirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while, I abided these exhausting rides with shy and silent resignation - choosing to avoid the gaze of other passengers and absorb myself in the glowing LED light of my phone. This self-isolation continued until one fateful encounter with an ironic marshrutka sign. The crush that day was particularly oppressive, and I was pushed against the wall of the cabin staring straight at a sign stuck to the wall which read: “The transport of standing passengers is strictly forbidden.” Marked with the stamp of municipal approval, this sign brought me to some larger questions about the existence of the marshrutka: Why are the marshrutkas which supposedly refuse to carry standing passengers so full of them? Is there anything about Novosibirsk itself that contributes to the excessive passengership? And, in general, what sets the marshrutka apart from other modes of transport in the city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;urban-planning-and-the-marshrutka&quot;&gt;Urban Planning and the Marshrutka&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to investigate the origins of the marshrutka crush is through studying the history of urban planning in Novosibirsk. The history of the city is marked by periods of rapid growth and constant change. According to an &lt;a href=&quot;http://nsk.novosibdom.ru/balandin_1893_1945&quot;&gt;architectural history&lt;/a&gt; of the city written by Sergei Nikolaevich Balandin, the city’s growth was fast-tracked by the construction of the Trans-Siberian railroad in the 1890s and the Altaian railroad running up from the South. After the Civil War, the city became the administrative center of Siberia, chosen as the regional headquarters of the Communist Party. During the 30s through the war, the city underwent rapid industrialization driven by the first five-year plan and the evacuation of factories and workers from the besieged Leningrad. From a village of about 20,000 in 1893, the city reached a population of 1,000,000 by 1960. This rapid population growth was accompanied by the often haphazard construction of housing for those working in the new administrative and industrial center. As the famous local architect A.D. Kriachkov mentions, architects were invited to the city almost exclusively to fix projects gone awry, rather than to plan the city’s development. This constant project of construction and re-construction has led many local historians to conclude that Novosibirsk is really 5 different cities in one - the new each constructed on the bones of the old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, these historical issues are compounded by modern-day issues with population density. Local historians &lt;a href=&quot;https://novcbs.ru/2018/03/22/maranin-i-oseev-k-novosibirsk-pyat-ischeznuvshix-gorodov-kniga-i-gorod-vestern/&quot;&gt;Igor Maranin and Konstantin Oseev&lt;/a&gt; attribute part of this problem to the geographic constraints on the city’s growth - the center of the city is confined by the Ob’ river to the West, the railroad tracks to the north, and the small river Kamenka to the South. According to a municipal study forecasting the city’s growth up until 2030, the territory of the city center comprises about 1% of the total territory of the city. This means that most people have to commute from the outside in. In addition to geographic constraints, the influx of international investment and development has led to the construction of “Novostroiki” and “Mnogoetazhki” (‘Housing Developments’ and ‘high-rises’) which have considerably increased population density in certain areas of the city. Many older generations of Novosibirtsy bemoan the consequences of these developments. One school teacher who I talked to mentioned that her school, originally built to teach 700 students, now teaches 1,700.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues with population density may explain the continued pervasiveness of the marshrutka. Historically, marshrutkas served to shuttle people from the center to the outskirts of cities - to so-called sleepy districts, the suburbs, and the countryside. In Novosibirsk, marshrutkas continue to fulfill this long distance function funneling people between surrounding districts and the comparatively small city center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;somewhere-between-private-and-public&quot;&gt;Somewhere Between Private and Public&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides pointing me to the history of Novosibirsk’s urban layout, marshrutkas also serve as a window into the public and private lives of Novosibirtsev. When you are stuffed into a marshrutka, unable to rotate head or body, there is nothing to do but look and listen. You are involuntarily immersed in the lives of others - staring at their phone contacts: mom, compote, brother, fish; their text conversations with loved ones: miss you, kitty; and their long goodbyes: давай, всё, до встречи, передай привет Кате, хорошо, всё давай, пока, до встречи. The private lives of all the passengers are open for everyone to partake in. Every word, glance, or shuffle will be noticed by others - that’s just the way things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open nature of the marshrutka makes it a hall of mirrors - reflecting the daily lives of passengers. In the early morning, the mood is solemn like that in a bedroom after the alarm has gone off. For the 9 o’clock commuters of the later morning, the marshrutka is an extension of the office - a place for business calls, negotiations, and meetings. After the end of the workday, the mood again shifts to the domestic front and many passengers can be found discussing what soup to cook for dinner. After 7 o’clock, the marshrutka becomes a pub frothing with the noise of banter, snickering, and long swigs of beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blend of public and private characteristic of the marshrutka has its origins in the collapse of the Soviet Union. According to historian &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teleskop-journal.spb.ru/files/dir_1/article_content1209827376193437file.pdf&quot;&gt;Anna Sanina&lt;/a&gt;, cities suddenly tasked with running a privatized municipal transport system contracted private companies to buy vehicles and hire drivers. Given the dire economic situation in Russia in the 90s, most cities did not have the resources to buy buses and pay to fuel and heat them. The GAZel’ marshrutka was an attractive alternative - given its smaller size it could be stored easily and cost less to heat and fuel. Not only this, but the marshrutka could charge a higher fare while not offering discounts to “льготники” (welfare-reliant passengers) like pensioners and students. The higher fare and lack of discounts contribute to a distinctly different atmosphere than that of other modes of public transport. While most municipal transport plays audio recordings appealing to “уважаемые пассажиры” (respected passengers), the relationship between driver and passenger on the average marshrutka is one of hostile negotiation and mutual disrespect. Passengers often yell at drivers who skip their stop; drivers talk about their passengers like sardines: “Ну чё, накидался?” (so’ve you packed it full?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interaction between driver and passengers is a source of great entertainment while riding the marshrutka. While there is a relatively limited vocabulary used to call out stops and switch places in the cabin, their meaning is not immediately clear. For this reason, I’ve compiled a brief glossary of marshrutka phraseology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Passenger or driver?&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Phrase&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Literal Translation&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Implied Meaning&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Passenger:&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Вы выходите?&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Are you getting off?&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;You're probably going to have to get out of my way.&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Driver:&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Продвиньте дальше в салон!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Move further into the cabin!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Cozy up to your neighbor!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Passenger:&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Передайте, пожалуйста!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Pass it please!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Grab this handful of change and bucket brigade it to the driver.&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Passenger:&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Заднюю откройте!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;Open the rear door!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;I'm not walking through this crowd of people!&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;/tbody&gt;

&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts-and-questions&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts and Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the madness, I am grateful to the marshrutka for forcing me to pay closer attention to Novosibirsk and Novosibirtsy. It is a harsh, but seemingly beloved mode of transport - a good example for teaching my students the meaning of the phrase “love-hate relationship.” The upside of the challenges presented by a marshrutka dominated transport system is a populace desiring change and willing to examine the problems inherent in the system more closely. I have found that many of my students have at least expressed a desire for change in the transportation system, if not an outright curiosity in the discipline of urban planning. In Moscow, marshrutkas such as those in Novosibirsk have been almost completely replaced by municipally run marshrutkas perhaps more deserving of the name “shuttle-bus” than “fixed-route taxi.” The question remains as to the future of the marshrutka in cities outside the capital. Will the urban ungulate go extinct all together, or will it continue to thrive on the paved and pot-holed plains? For now, it seems, the marshrutka is here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’d like to acknowledge the help of Olesya Valger in clarifying some of my questions about the municipal transport system. Also, thank you to Alexander White for encouraging me to write something about this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shuba</name></author><summary type="html">The Marshrutka Stampede in Novosibirsk</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digging the Dust of Shakespeare’s Bones in Crystal Springs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2016/12/01/Digging-the-Dust-of-Shakespeare's-Bones-in-Crystal-Springs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digging the Dust of Shakespeare's Bones in Crystal Springs" /><published>2016-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2016/12/01/Digging-the-Dust-of-Shakespeare's-Bones-in-Crystal-Springs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bmare.github.io/blog/2016/12/01/Digging-the-Dust-of-Shakespeare's-Bones-in-Crystal-Springs">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.reed.edu/reed_magazine/december2016/articles/apocrypha/images/shakespeareIsland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;“Reed Students Cry Out Against Shakespeare Isle ‘Desecration.’” Photo from the Oregon Journal, Sept. 28, 1950.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September, 1950, a roving band of Reed students outfitted with lutes and the drama department’s best shot at Elizabethan attire descended on Crystal Springs Island to jump a cyclone fence that had been recently erected by the Rhododendron Society. With a great vertical leap, these students protested the desecration of their beloved “Shakespeare Island” by knavish and unworthy barricades.
Nowadays the bones of this controversy lie deep under the soil, goose-crap, and rhododendron roots of Crystal Springs. Today students know the island (really more like a peninsula) as the section of the Rhodie Garden that sits across a scenic wooden bridge where “fair is ‘fowl’ and ‘fowl’ is fair.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shakespearean roots of the island were sown in 1930, when the LaBarre Shakespeare Club established a Shakespearean garden on the premises. Reed president Dr. Norman F. Coleman was present at the opening ceremony and helped plant the island’s first Shakespearean sapling—an English oak in honor of that oak whose antique root peeped out along a brawling brook in &lt;em&gt;As You Like It&lt;/em&gt;. The garden truly flourished when Prof. Barry Cerf [English 1921–48] rallied student support for the project in 1932.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students in the ’30s considered the island an unofficial part of campus, where they sought reverie and communion with nature. Shakespeare Island appeared in the 1933 student publication “Campus Views,” which included a photo of a student perched in a willow tree by the lake. A 1950 &lt;em&gt;Quest&lt;/em&gt; article dubbed the land mass a “Walden” for Reed students and a holy site for the deliberate “religious practice” of the “Reed College Thoreau.” (We aren’t sure exactly what this means, but we get the drift.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the tempestuous times brought on by the Depression and World War II, Shakespeare Island grew wild. Reed students doubled their toil and trouble, and journeyed there seeking communion of a different kind. The overgrown isle became known as a nocturnal haven for campfire songs fueled by kegs of Blitz-Weinhard and as a “couples’ retreat” for fulsome frolicking in the fe
urns.
Eastmoreland residents quickly became acquainted with the rites of the Reed student on the island and, when asked about its purpose, mused that it was where students retired “for intellectual conversation and whatever other activities occur to a Reed College student when the moonlight is too weak to read Shelley in.” These residents were thus delighted when, in June, 1950, Portland City Commissioner Ormond Bean judged Reed students’ endeavors on the island a case of “Love’s Labour’s Lost” and wrote a municipal ordinance handing it over to the Rhododendron Society, which promptly fenced it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The barricades provoked outrage from students, who proceeded to stage one of the more unusual protests in Reed’s history. Having scaled the fence, breeches intact, students chanted “For Jesus’ sake forbear—Keep Shakespeare out of Shakespeare Island? Never!” Reporters from the &lt;em&gt;Oregonian&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Oregon Daily Journal&lt;/em&gt; rushed to the scene, nine-ironed golfers swore to have seen “pixies” across the lake, and long-suffering Eastmoreland neighbors dismissed the spectacle as much ado about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing in the &lt;em&gt;Quest,&lt;/em&gt; students argued that the Rhododendron Society would not promote the ecological health of the island or the Portland public. In a column titled &lt;em&gt;A Serpent’s Tooth&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reed.edu/reed-magazine/in-memoriam/obituaries/august1994/william-h-dickey-1951.html&quot;&gt;Bill Dickey&lt;/a&gt; ’51&lt;/strong&gt; declared the rhododendron an invasive species comparable to the Japanese beetle and accused Commissioner Bean of attempting to woo the public with azaleas. Local papers such as the &lt;em&gt;Oregonian&lt;/em&gt; responded with scathing remarks about the Reed College “cut-ups.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, however, the protests availed naught. Shakespeare Island went from on-campus, to off-campus, to off-limits for Reed students. It was thus fitting that students chanted the verses from the Bard’s own epitaph: Good frend for Jesus sake forbeare, To digg the dust encloased heare; Bleste be the man that spares thes stones, And curst be he that moves my bones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reed.edu/reed_magazine/december2016/articles/apocrypha/traditions_myths_and_legends.html&quot;&gt;Reed Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The Bard</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>